Finding Aid for John L. Kavanaugh papers, 1970-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John L. Kavanaugh papers 1970-2011, 1990s-2000s
Kavanaugh, John L.
718 MB
4 linear feet (in 5 boxes)
2011124 Aa 2
Detroit social activist involved in GLBT organizations and activities. The collection consists of correspondence, essays and articles, e-mails, conference materials, organizational records, publications and articles on the subjects of GLBT history, gay civil rights, gay marriage, interracial and interfaith marriage, GLBT families, sexual and gender equality, violence against GLBT persons, religion and homosexuality, gay clergy, clergy with AIDS, and violence against GLBT persons. The collection also includes materials related to the development of public transportation in the Detroit Metropolitan area; election campaigns and vote suppression of ethnic minorities; and U.S. and international politics and economy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by John Kavanaugh (donor no. 10372 ) in March 2011.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
John L. Kavanaugh, a Detroit, Mich. resident and a life-long social activist, was a one-time member of the Brothers of Holy Cross within the Roman Catholic Church. Since 1968, he has been active in the GLBT movement. He served as a member of ONE, Detroit's Gay Liberation Front (serving as coordinator from 1970 to 1972); a founding member and the first lay head of Metropolitan Community Church in Detroit; a member of Integrity, the GLBT caucus within the Episcopal Church; a member of the Detroit chapter of Black and White Men Together (BWMT); and a member of the Triangle Foundation in Detroit. Throughout his activist career, John Kavanaugh has corresponded with numerous GLBT and religious leaders, organizations, and publications on various religious, social and political subjects.
Public transit development is another area of interest for Kavanaugh. He has been a participant in community meetings and corresponded on the subject with members of Detroit metropolitan community, local and state government and organizations.
In 2004 Kavanaugh published a book Welcome to the gay age (Tucson, Ariz. :Iceni Books, 2004).
The collection, spanning 40 years of John Kavanaugh's activism, documents both the history and challenges faced by the Michigan and national GLBT community, as well issues facing the area's racial and ethnic minorities. Of most value, the collection provides documentation regarding the position of various denominations on questions of homosexuality and gay and interracial marriage; racial and ethnic discrimination, and voters' suppression based on race and ethnicity. Kavanaugh's correspondence includes letters and hard copies of e-mails, many of them sent to individual clergy and to groups of citizens. His writings are sometimes represented in form of a self-published newsletter or e-newsletter (e.g. The bead reader and The missing lines). The collection contains a great number of non-mainstream publications, as well as articles and clippings from obscure and rare periodicals. The collection also includes a significant amount of material on the subject of public transit in Michigan, specifically, in the city of Detroit.
The collection is organized into five series: Issues; Black and White Men Together; Religion; Public Transit; and Digital materials.
Subjects:
Kavanaugh, John L.; National Association of Black and White Men Together.; St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); Catholics--Michigan--Detroit.; Episcopalians--Michigan--Detroit.; Gay liberation movement--History.; Homosexuality--Religious aspects--Christianity.; Local transit--Michigan--Detroit.; Same-sex marriage.; Transportation--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; CD-ROMs.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Issues
  The Issues series contains Kavanaugh's correspondence, essays and articles (written by Kavanaugh and others), materials of organizations and non-mainstream media items collected by Kavanaugh over the period of 40 years. The series also contains issues of Kavanaugh's self-published periodical The missing lines and correspondence related to this publication. Additional issues of The missing lines can be found in electronic format in the Electronic materials series. The majority of materials in this series relate to the subject of history of the GLBT movement, homosexuality, gay marriage and the church's position on homosexuality, as well as voters suppression based on racial discrimination. Also included here are selected records of the Michigan Welfare Rights Organization and the New Center North housing community in Detroit. In addition, this series contains an audiocassette with music from an undated Gay Arts Workshop.
  - Correspondence 1994-2011 with gaps, 4 folders (Box 1)
    (see also Digital materials series)
  - Gay Activist Alliance (Box 1)
  - Gay clergy 1980s-2000s with gaps, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Gay marriage and family 1989-2006, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - GLBT movement history (Box 1)
  - Michigan Welfare Rights Organization 2007-2009 (Box 1)
  - New Center North 1999-2009 with gaps (Box 1)
  - News files 1972-2006, 5 folders (Box 1)
    (see also oversize box 5)
  - Religious right 1994-2003 with gaps (Box 1)
  - The religious right in Michigan politics by Russ Bellant, galley proof, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Scripture and homosexuality 1990s-2000s with gaps (Box 1)
  - Some missing lines, 2007-2010, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - The Triangle Foundation of Michigan 1992-2005 with gaps, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Violence against LGBT persons 1990s-2000s (Box 2)
  - Voters' suppression 2007-2011, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous materials, including a photograph (Box 2)
  - Audio materials: Gay Arts Workshop music (audio cassette), undated (Box 2)
- Black and White Men Together (BWMT)
  The Black and White Men Together (BWMT) series contains Kavanaugh's correspondence with the BWMT National Association and regional chapters; his essays and articles prepared by him in preparation for NABWMT conferences; NABWMT administrative records, including by-laws, standing and financial reports, and manuals; NABWMT conference materials and publications, as well as materials of regional chapters of BWMT; miscellaneous publications on the subject of racism and homophobia by individual authors and organizations.
  - Articles by Kavanaugh 1983-1996, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - BWMT regional meetings and seminars, late 1980s-2000s scattered (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1989-2011 with gaps, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Men of Color motivational group 1990s-2000s (Box 2)
  - NABWMT materials
    - Administrative records 1980s-2000s, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - NABWMT National Convention 2002 (Box 2)
    - NABWMT Publications
      - NABWMT Journal, 1988-1992, 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Quarterly, 1996-2006 scattered (Box 2)
      - NABWMT's identity crisis: evolution or viral infection, by Colin J. Gibson, 1996 (Box 2)
      - Resisting racism: an action guide, Gerald L. Mallon, ed., 1991 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous publications by NABWMT and its chapters 1996-2006 scattered (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous materials by other groups and newspaper clippings 1979-2011 scattered, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Religion
  The Religion series has two sub-series: the Episcopal Church (larger) and the Roman Catholic Church. Materials in both include Kavanaugh's correspondence with Episcopal and Catholic institutions and clergy, and his writings about homosexuality and the church's position on the subject of homosexuality, homosexuality in scripture, gay marriage, families of gays and lesbians, religious services for GLBT parishioners, gay clergy, sexual abuse and the church, and many others. The Episcopal Church files also includes records of the St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church, materials of the Metropolitan Community Church of Detroit; Kavanaugh's self-published periodical The bead reader publications of Integrity, an organization of GLBT Episcopalians, Integrity news & notes and The voice of Integrity. Within the St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church files are a few undated photographs of church members.
  - Episcopal Church
    - Correspondence 1980s-2000s (Box 2)
    - Episcopal Diocese of Michigan 1970s-1999, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Essays 1980s-1990s, undated (Box 3)
    - Lesbian and Gay Christian Movement 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
    - Publications
      - The bead reader, 1975-1980, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - The bead reader, 1982-1983, 1986, 1988, 1997, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Integrity news & notes, July 1987, Summer 1990 (Box 3)
      - The voice of Integrity, 1994-1995, 2002-2006 with gaps, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - The witness (issues and correspondence with), 1990-2003 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous publications 1970s-1990s, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous publications 1970s-1990s, undated (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings 1970s-2000s scattered (Box 3)
    - St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church
      - Administrative records 1989-1990, 1996-2002, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1996, 2002 (Box 3)
      - History (Box 3)
      - Religious services, programs and events 1980s-2000s (Box 3)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 3)
    - Under One Roof Conference 1987 (Box 3)
  - Metropolitan Community Church of Detroit 1978-2005 (Box 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church
    - Correspondence 1970s, 1993-2011 with gaps, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Essays by Kavanaugh 1990, 2002, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Public transit
  The Public transit series mainly contains materials on the subject of public transportation mainly in the Detroit metropolitan area but also including some materials about public transportation in other parts of Michigan, namely in Ann Arbor. The series contains correspondence; public transit planning documents, drafts and maps prepared by state and local government organizations; administrative records and correspondence of Transportation Riders United (TRU), a non-profit charitable organization, and issues of its official publication Moving forward.
  - Correspondence 1994-2011, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Moving forward, 2002-2008 with gaps (Box 4)
  - Planning 1999-2007, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG) 1999, 2001 undated (Box 4)
  - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG) (Box 5)
  - Transportation Riders United (TRU)
    - Board of Directors 2005-2006 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 2004-2007, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Records 1999-2009 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous publications 1990s-2000s (Box 4)
- Electronic materials: CD-ROM, 568 MB; 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 4)
  The Electronic materials series contains 1 CD (568 MG) with correspondence on various subjects reflected in previous series, photographs and amateur photo images of and possibly by John Kavanaugh, as well as commercially made images; business records of Coat & Simms Enterprises, Inc. Assisted Living Center; 2007 issues of Some missing lines (some duplicate and additional to the hard copies included in the Issues series), and e-mail correspondence.
  - E-mail, 113 MB
    (E-mail back up (in .pst format))
  - Media-Image, 1.32 MB
    (1 image (in .jpg format))
  - My Documents Folder, 448 MB; 235 files ( (in 6 folders)
    (Correspondence, photographs and amateur images of John Kavanaugh and other individuals, as well as commercially made images, business plans and forms (formats include .jpg, .bmp, .wmv, .doc, .xls, .pdf))
  - Some missing lines, 2007, 121 files 2.65 MB
    (2007 issues and accompanying correspondence (in .eml format))
- Digital materials
  The Digital Materials is comprised of two subseries: Issues and Personal Materials. The Issues subseries contains drafts of correspondence, email, articles, essays, eNewsletters (including copies of "Some Missing Lines"), flyers and other material related to the various issues with which Kavanaugh was involved: gay rights, religion, public transit, elections, voter suppression, and urban development among others. As such, these materials will have varying degrees of overlap with other series in the collection. The Personal Materials subseries includes digital photographs collected by Kavanaugh or taken of him and associates as well as some video footage of his home and neighborhood.
  - Issues, BHL deposit ID 2011124_0001
    - Documents: essays, draft correspondence, flyers and memoranda relating to various religious, transit, and socioeconomic issues 2006-2012
      (includes a manuscript of the essay collection "Cain Today" as well as materials for New Center North Neighbors association)
    - Email Correspondence (incoming and outgoing)
      - AAA-Test-Cannot Reach 2011
      - Alternative Political Parties 2011
      - BAMN (Coalition to Defend Affirmative Action, Integration & Immigrant Rights, and Fight for Equality By Any Means Necessary) 2011-2012
      - Barack-Government 2 2010-2012
      - Barrow Campaign 2009-2012
        (correspondence from and related to Detroit mayoral candidate Tom Barrow)
      - Bentley Historical Library 2010-2012
      - Black Issues 2006-2012
      - Bush-Government 2006-2011
      - Catholic Church 2007-2012
      - CDC (Central Detroit Christian Community Development Corporation) Flower Project 2007-2011
      - Church 2005-2012
        (includes correspondence related to homosexuality and religion)
      - Color Of Change (grassroots African-American political organization) 2007-2012
      - Corporate Issues 2009-2012
      - Draft 2012
      - Elizabeth Warren 2011-2012
      - Email Back Up
        - Inbox 2010
        - Barack Government 2010
        - Some Missing Lines 2007-2010
        - Stolen Votes 2005-2008
          (voter suppression issues)
      - Episcopal Church 2008-2012
      - Essay Materials 2012
      - Essays 2012
      - Food Versus Synthetic Supplements 2012
      - Fox Network 2011-2012
      - Freer House-Pres Wayne 2010-2012
        (correspondence related to the Charles Lang Freer house and Preservation Wayne, an architectural preservation organization)
      - Haiti 2010-2011
      - Hansen Clarke (U.S. Representative) 2010-2012
      - Harris Family 2011
      - Hate Speech Interaction 2011
      - Health Insurance Government Plans 2009-2012
      - Hilles Family 2005-2012
        (includes genealogical information)
      - Integrity 2008-2009
        ("Integrity Southeast Michigan" e-newsletters and related correspondence)
      - Internet Corporate Censorship 2007-2012
      - Kavanaugh 2007-2011
      - Koch Brothers 2010-2011
      - Latin American Issues 2008-2011
      - LGBT Issues 2005-2012
      - Major Vote Activists 2010
      - Mattie Joes (St. Matthew's and St. Joseph's Episcopal Church, Detroit) 2007-2012
        (correspondence about the church and related events and activities)
      - MCC-Detroit (Metropolitan Community Church of Detroit) 2007-2011
      - MCHR (Michigan Coalition for Human Rights) 2007-2012
      - Media Issues 2006-2012
      - Michigan Politics 2011-2012
      - Michigan Welfare Rights 2006-2012
      - NABWMT (National Association of Black and White Men Together) 2005-2012
      - New Center North Neighbors 2007-2012
      - Occupy Wall Street 2011-2012
      - ONE, Incorporated (early U.S. gay-rights organization) 2006-2009
        (includes correspondence related to a Detroit oral history project for the ONE Archives in Los Angeles)
      - Orthodox Church 2010
      - Personal 2005-2012
      - Progressives 2008-2012
      - Quakers 2011
      - Redistricting Issues 2011
      - Reply To Kevin (Kavanaugh) 2007-2011
      - Republican Party 2011-2012
      - Republican Vote Suppression 2011
      - Ruth Ellis Center (support center for Lesbian, Gay, Bi-atractional, Transgender and Questioning youth) 2010
      - Safeco Insurance 2009-2011
      - Scarab Club (an artists' club, gallery, and studio in the Cultural Center Historic District of Detroit) 2010-2012
      - Some Missing Lines 2 2010-2012
      - Some Missing Lines Introductory Package 2009-2010
      - Sr Joanette 2005-2011
        (correspondence with Sister Joanetter Nitz, of the Racine, WI Dominicans)
      - Stealing America 2008
        (correspondence related to election reform)
      - Stolen Votes 2 2010-2012
        (eNewsletters and related correspondence on voter suppression)
      - The Michigan Citizen 2009-2011
      - Tim Retzloff 2010-2011
        (correspondence related to research on the history of the gay rights movement)
      - To Be Printed 2011
      - Transit MWRO (Michigan Welfare Rights Organization) Committee 2009-2012
      - Transit Issues 2007-2012
      - Transportation Riders United TRU (non-profit organization dedicated to improving transportation access and mobility in Greater Detroit) 2005-2012
      - Truthout (alternative news organization) 2008-2012
      - Union Issues 2008-2012
      - US Social Forum 2009-2011
      - Venezuela Issues 2006-2011
      - Voice of Detroit (independent newspaper) 2010-2012
      - Welcome To The Gay Age-Related Concepts 2005-2011
      - Wisconsin Political Issues 2011
      - Womens Issues 2007-2012
      - World Social Forum 2005-2011
      - Wow And Bru 2011-2012
        (correspondence related to various social issues)
    - Some Missing Lines eNewsletters 2007
      (includes email correspondence related to eNewsletters)
  - Personal Materials, BHL deposit ID 2011124_0001
    - Pictures 2007-2010
      (images of John Kavanaugh and associates; includes images collected by Kavanaugh)
      (BHL deposit ID 2011124_0001)
    - Videos circa 2008
      (video footage of Kavanaugh and his residence)